<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Courses | Fragmented Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/categories/courses/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-25T14:29:06+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Knut Jackowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: HTML5 Canvas - From Pixels to Animation]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2017/03/25/html5-canvas-from-pixels-to-animation/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-25T13:34:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2017/03/25/html5-canvas-from-pixels-to-animation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I finished the little course <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/html5-canvas--ud292">HTML5 Canvas - From Pixels to Animation</a> on Udacity. While the technical details were not really new to me, as I have used the canvas before, it was a good refresher on the use of graphics and videos on the canvas without using any libraries.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The course is not very long, only two lessons, each having roughly the same size as weekly lessons in paced moocs, but this is, as all Udacity courses are, a self-paced course, so it is perfectly fine to work through all the material in more then one week per lesson or even go through it all in one long learning session.</p>

<p>In contrast to some older Udacity courses this course does not work towards one final project, building it up from the beginning of the course until it is finished at the end, but instead there are some smaller projects along the way. I think this is beneficial to make the course accessable for different learners:
Having one project to work on from the beginning until the end is nice for people who have the time to go through the course in one go or at least in the time it would take someone taking a similar course on a weekly lesson basis. It helps them learn to build complex systems and not only small examples, but it also gets a lot more difficult if there is some time between the lessons, because the learner has something else to do. I have actually given up on more than one course like this, because study breaks caused by other daily life responsibilities led to me spending more time on trying to get into the projects again then on the actual content of these courses.</p>

<p>This course instead has two smaller projects, one for each lesson:</p>

<p>The first lesson shows the basics of working with the canvas element, how to set up a webserver to locally run the code (some of the topics require either a local server or a https connection and will not run when you just open the html-file in your browser), how to draw and how to load assets. The final project of this is a Meme-Maker that combines images with text.</p>

<p>The second lesson dives into the topic of the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Canvas_API/Tutorial/Pixel_manipulation_with_canvas">pixel array</a>, that is part of the ImageData object, working with video data and animation, providing all the necessary building blocks of programming a game. During the lesson the examples move around the topic of image and video manipulation, like these two sketches:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://doxanthropos.github.io/sketchbook/2017031901/">Photo manipulator 01</a></li>
<li><a href="https://doxanthropos.github.io/sketchbook/2017032001/">Photo manipulator 02</a></li>
</ul>


<p>In general I would say this is a nice basic course that covers a lot of the possibilities of the HTML5 canvas in a short time. To go deeper into any of the shown directions, for example game programming, a lot more material will be needed, but after this course one will be able to have an idea how to go on about that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Minimalist Physics Engine]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/a-minimalist-physics-engine/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-15T13:04:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/a-minimalist-physics-engine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/shiffman">Daniel Shiffman</a> surprised me yesterday in his course &ldquo;<a href="https://www.kadenze.com/courses/the-nature-of-code">The Nature of Code</a>&rdquo; with a most simple concept of a physics engine in two lines of JavaScript:</p>

<pre><code class="Javascript">pos.add(vel);
vel.add(acc);
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<script src="http://doxanthropos.github.io/javascripts/p5.js"></script>


<script src="http://doxanthropos.github.io/javascripts/p5.dom.js"></script>


<p>These two lines have the three components(vectors) that are necessary to describe movement: position, velocity and acceleration:</p>

<ol>
<li>Objects have a position (pos).</li>
<li>The position gets changed (add) by velocity (vel).</li>
<li>The velocity gets changed (add) by acceleration (acc).</li>
</ol>


<p>The add-method comes from <a href="https://p5js.org">P5JS</a> and belongs to the <a href="linktothevectorobjectsdocumentation">vector object</a>.</p>

<p>Of course to use it in a sketch, there is more to write than these two lines, but they contain the core concept. For example, this code from the course creates a circle that looks like it is falling, because it accelerates downward:</p>

<pre><code class="Javascript">function Walker(x,y) {
    this.pos = createVector(x,y);
    this.vel = createVector(0,0);
    this.acc = createVector(0,0.1); 

    this.update = function(){
        this.vel.add(this.acc);
        this.pos.add(this.vel);
    }

    this.display = function(){
        fill(255);
        ellipse(this.pos.x,this.pos.y,48,48);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<center>
<button onclick="setup();" style="align:right;">Restart</button>
</center>


<div id="p5canvas"></div>


<script>
var w;
function setup() {
    var cnv = createCanvas($("#p5canvas").width(),360);
    w = new Walker(width/2,0);
    cnv.parent("p5canvas");
}

function draw() {
    background(51);
    w.display();
    w.update();
  
}

function Walker(x,y) {
    this.pos = createVector(x,y);
    this.vel = createVector(0,0);
    this.acc = createVector(0,0.1); 

    this.update = function(){
        this.vel.add(this.acc);
        this.pos.add(this.vel);
    }

    this.display = function(){
        fill(255);
        ellipse(this.pos.x,this.pos.y,48,48);
    }
}

</script>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Advanced Styling With Responsive Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/04/10/review-advanced-styling-with-responsive-design/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-10T11:38:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/04/10/review-advanced-styling-with-responsive-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I finished the course &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/responsivedesign">Advanced Styling with Responsive Design</a>&rdquo; on Coursera. It is the fourth course of the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/web-design">Web Design for Everybody</a>&rdquo; specialization from the University of Michigan and it is taught by Colleen van Lent like the other three courses. Despite the fact, that the technical knowledge this course provides was not all new to me, I think I still have learned a lot.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When I discovered the courses of the specialization, I had a look at the first two and skipped them, because they seemed to be on a more introductory level, than what I thought, that I would need. The first one that I actually took and also finished was the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/javascript">Interactivity with JavaScript</a>&rdquo; course, the third one in the series and after that the responsive design course.</p>

<p>The content of both courses was mostly not new to me and I don&rsquo;t think, that I have seen JavaScript or CSS in one of them, that I had not seen or even written before.</p>

<p>What made these courses still worthwhile were the lectures by Colleen, because she tried very successfully, not only to talk about the technical details, but to provide always the bigger picture. For example, I knew how to use Bootstrap grids and I had heard about &ldquo;mobile first&rdquo;, but it took this course for me to really understand the connection between the two.</p>

<p>With this connection between the big picture and the details I have gained a lot of new understanding of how to think about web development.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.umich.edu/">University of Michigan</a> seems to have good luck in hiring their teachers. I have been kind of a fan of <a href="http://www.dr-chuck.com/">Doctor Chuck</a> for some time now (we use <a href="https://www.imsglobal.org/activity/learning-tools-interoperability">LTI</a> quite often at work and he has done a lot to popularize that standard), who teaches the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/python">Python for Everybody</a>&rdquo; specialization (I will probably talk about that in another post), but he is clearly not the only great teacher at this University.</p>

<p>I would recommend this course (and the whole specialization) to anybody who wants to learn web design or web development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Adventures in Web Animations]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/adventures-in-web-animation/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-08T13:06:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/adventures-in-web-animation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I played through the course &ldquo;<a href="https://www.codeschool.com/courses/adventures-in-web-animations">Adventures in Web Animations</a>&rdquo; on Codeschool.com. This was my first Codeschool.com course and I mostly took it, because it was the free weekend, I had nothing else to do, being sick and at home, and because web animation was a topic, that I knew not very well.</p>

<p>The lessons have been rather simple, with easy multiple choice questions and very guided coding excercises, but the instructor managed to explain the different parts of animation in great detail. While one cannot expect to learn this topic to the bone in one very short course, I have the impression that I now have a good overview how to animate with css and where to look for helpful resources on the way.</p>

<p>What I really liked was that this course has an accompanying screencast called &ldquo;<a href="https://www.codeschool.com/screencasts/soup-to-bits-adventures-in-web-animations">Soup to Bits: Adventures in Web Animations</a>&rdquo;. Usually I am not that much of a fan of screencasts for learning, but this one hit the right spot: I shows the instructor of the course Alyssa Nicoll together with another Codeschool.com developer Dan Denney working on an example website that is somewhat complete, but as they conclude, missing animations. So you can follow them for around an hour, how they put together the animations an this website, how they make mistakes and debug them, how they come to decide on the specifics of the animations and so on, until the website is ready. And if you really want to try your new skills, you can do the same, because the website they work on is available as a github repository.</p>

<p>These two parts, the course and the screencast, really work well together. The course sets the ground on which it is possible to go through the screencast without explaining everything and the screencast gives some meat the the bones of still dry and untested knowledge from the course.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creative Coding With Processing ... Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2015/08/09/creative-coding-again/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-09T14:53:56+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2015/08/09/creative-coding-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week was the start of two courses (<a href="https://www.futurelearn.com/courses/creative-coding">Creative Coding on Futurelearn</a> and <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/digitalmedia">Creative Programming for Digital Media &amp; Mobile Apps on Coursera.org</a> about creative programming in <a href="https://processing.org/">Processing</a>) and I blogged about them in my <a href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2014/06/13/blogging-about-processing/">main blog</a>.
Since I have already done some of the assignments some time ago, I focused on some things that I knew about, but did not do so far.</p>

<h2>Creating gifs</h2>

<p>There are basically two simple ways to create gifs from Processing sketches (that&rsquo;s what the single programs are called in the Processing world) and both are explained by <a href="http://www.jeromeherr.space/">Jerome Herr</a> on <a href="http://p5art.tumblr.com/">his Tumblr</a>:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://p5art.tumblr.com/post/98291300538/turning-a-processing-sketch-into-an-animated-gif">Save single frame images and combine them later with other tools</a> or</li>
<li><a href="http://p5art.tumblr.com/post/76979034572/exporting-sketches-as-animated-gifs-in-processing">use a library that creates the gif while the program is running</a>.</li>
</ol>


<p>I tried both and both worked fine, at least in part. I was able to install <a href="http://www.lcdf.org/gifsicle/">gifsicle</a>, but it would not run properly so I did what anyone would do who already has some experience with <a href="http://www.imagemagick.org/index.php">ImageMagick</a>, I used the usual <a href="https://www.tjhsst.edu/~dhyatt/supercomp/n401a.html">convert</a> to do the trick.</p>

<p>I will need some more tries to determine, which method to use more because they seem to have different effects on the speed of execution of the sketches. This doesn&rsquo;t really matter, when the animations are generated by code alone, because the framerate will be the same for the exection as for the gif, but it produces much different output when human interaction is part of the sketch.</p>

<p>So probably there will be more here about <a href="https://processing.org/">Processing</a> in the near future. By the way, the mentioned Tumblr from Jerome also has a <a href="http://p5art.tumblr.com/tutorials">nice list of learning ressources for Processing</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
