<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Webdev, | Fragmented Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/categories/webdev/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-22T14:04:51+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Knut Jackowski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Advanced Styling With Responsive Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/04/10/review-advanced-styling-with-responsive-design/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-10T11:38:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/04/10/review-advanced-styling-with-responsive-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I finished the course &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/responsivedesign">Advanced Styling with Responsive Design</a>&rdquo; on Coursera. It is the fourth course of the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/web-design">Web Design for Everybody</a>&rdquo; specialization from the University of Michigan and it is taught by Colleen van Lent like the other three courses. Despite the fact, that the technical knowledge this course provides was not all new to me, I think I still have learned a lot.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When I discovered the courses of the specialization, I had a look at the first two and skipped them, because they seemed to be on a more introductory level, than what I thought, that I would need. The first one that I actually took and also finished was the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/javascript">Interactivity with JavaScript</a>&rdquo; course, the third one in the series and after that the responsive design course.</p>

<p>The content of both courses was mostly not new to me and I don&rsquo;t think, that I have seen JavaScript or CSS in one of them, that I had not seen or even written before.</p>

<p>What made these courses still worthwhile were the lectures by Colleen, because she tried very successfully, not only to talk about the technical details, but to provide always the bigger picture. For example, I knew how to use Bootstrap grids and I had heard about &ldquo;mobile first&rdquo;, but it took this course for me to really understand the connection between the two.</p>

<p>With this connection between the big picture and the details I have gained a lot of new understanding of how to think about web development.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.umich.edu/">University of Michigan</a> seems to have good luck in hiring their teachers. I have been kind of a fan of <a href="http://www.dr-chuck.com/">Doctor Chuck</a> for some time now (we use <a href="https://www.imsglobal.org/activity/learning-tools-interoperability">LTI</a> quite often at work and he has done a lot to popularize that standard), who teaches the &ldquo;<a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/python">Python for Everybody</a>&rdquo; specialization (I will probably talk about that in another post), but he is clearly not the only great teacher at this University.</p>

<p>I would recommend this course (and the whole specialization) to anybody who wants to learn web design or web development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Adventures in Web Animations]]></title>
    <link href="http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/adventures-in-web-animation/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-08T13:06:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://doxanthropos.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/adventures-in-web-animation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I played through the course &ldquo;<a href="https://www.codeschool.com/courses/adventures-in-web-animations">Adventures in Web Animations</a>&rdquo; on Codeschool.com. This was my first Codeschool.com course and I mostly took it, because it was the free weekend, I had nothing else to do, being sick and at home, and because web animation was a topic, that I knew not very well.</p>

<p>The lessons have been rather simple, with easy multiple choice questions and very guided coding excercises, but the instructor managed to explain the different parts of animation in great detail. While one cannot expect to learn this topic to the bone in one very short course, I have the impression that I now have a good overview how to animate with css and where to look for helpful resources on the way.</p>

<p>What I really liked was that this course has an accompanying screencast called &ldquo;<a href="https://www.codeschool.com/screencasts/soup-to-bits-adventures-in-web-animations">Soup to Bits: Adventures in Web Animations</a>&rdquo;. Usually I am not that much of a fan of screencasts for learning, but this one hit the right spot: I shows the instructor of the course Alyssa Nicoll together with another Codeschool.com developer Dan Denney working on an example website that is somewhat complete, but as they conclude, missing animations. So you can follow them for around an hour, how they put together the animations an this website, how they make mistakes and debug them, how they come to decide on the specifics of the animations and so on, until the website is ready. And if you really want to try your new skills, you can do the same, because the website they work on is available as a github repository.</p>

<p>These two parts, the course and the screencast, really work well together. The course sets the ground on which it is possible to go through the screencast without explaining everything and the screencast gives some meat the the bones of still dry and untested knowledge from the course.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
